Finding Aid for the Amy Frances Brown Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Amy Frances Brown Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0056
2.5 Linear Feet
Biographical Note
Amy Frances Brown was born on a farm near Galesburg, Illinois. She earned her Bachelor of Education at Western Illinois State in 1930, her M.S. in Nursing from Western Reserve in 1940, and in 1955 her Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. She joined the faculty at Vanderbilt University School of Nursing in 1941. Her career encompassed nursing and the development of nursing curricula, teaching, and scientific writing. Her published works include Curriculum Development (1960), Clinical Instruction (1949), Research in Nursing (1958) and in 1945 her most notable book, Medical Nursing. In addition, she was a highly requested guest speaker for various medical conferences across the country.
In 1965, the Amy Frances Brown Prize for Excellence in Writing was established. This award was given to juniors and seniors annually who met course requirements, and submitted the best comprehensive scientific writing.
Amy Frances Brown retired in 1974 as Professor of Medical Surgical Nursing, Emerita after 33 years of service to the Vanderbilt University medical community. She died on December 14, 1983.
Scope and Content Note
The Amy Frances Brown Papers contain various documents relating to her professional career at Vanderbilt for the years 1951-1970. The papers are contained in 10 Hollinger boxes (4.17 linear feet) and are comprised of these series relating to her academic career:
- Academic Career - Outgoing Correspondence, 1961-1963
  - October, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - January-December, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - January, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - February, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - March, 1963 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - March, 1963 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - April, 1963 (1 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - April, 1963 (2 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - April, 1963 (3 of 3) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - May, 1963 (1 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - May, 1963 (2 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - May, 1963 (3 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - May, 1963 (4 of 4) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - June, 1963 (1 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - June, 1963 (2 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - June, 1963 (3 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - June, 1963 (4 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - June, 1963 (5 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - June, 1963 (6 of 6) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - July, 1963 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - July, 1963 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - September, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - October, 1963 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - October, 1963 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - November-December, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Academic Career-Outgoing Correspondence, 1964-1970
  - January-August, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - September -November, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - December, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - January-February, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - March- April, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - April, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - May - July, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - August, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - September, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - October, 1965 (1 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - October, 1965 (2 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - October, 1965 (3 of 3) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - November-December, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - January, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - February-March, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - April-May, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - July - August, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - September-October, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - November-December, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - January-June, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - September-October, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - November, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - February- December, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - January-February, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - August-September, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - October, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - November, 1970 (1 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - November, 1970 (2 of 2) (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Academic Career-Outgoing Correspondence, 1971-1982
  - January, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - February, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - March, 1971 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - March, 1971 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - April, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - May, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - June, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - July, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - August-September, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - October-November, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - December, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - January, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - February, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - March-April, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - May, 1972 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - May, 1972 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - July-August, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - September-October, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - February-April, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - May-July, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - September, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - November-December, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Office of the Provost Correspondence, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - January-March, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - April-June, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - August, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - September-November, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - January-February, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - June, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - September-December, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - February-March, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - July-August, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - November-December, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Academic Career- Incoming Correspondence (A-R), undated
  - Acker-Adler, Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Archer-Axelrod, Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bahr- Bernstein, Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Birney-Burt, Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cannon-Christman, Undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Clark-Crawford, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Deets-Donley, Undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Drosness-Dyke, Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Elliot-Fisher, Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Garrett-Gerrard, Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Golden-Gunther, Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Hangel-Hereford, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Hinton-Hulburt, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ingmire-Iverson, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Jackson-Josephson, Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Kadushin-Kent, Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Killip-Knuttgen, Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Krakow-Kurland, Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ladimer-Littlestone, Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Loftin-Luykx, Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Magregor-May, Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - McAllister-Mcvey, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Meadow-Milne, Undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Mobley-Morse, Undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Mulaney-Muth, Undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Nassau-Nye, Undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - O‘Conner-Ott, Undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Paffenbarger-Pflanz, Undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Phillips-Platou, Undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Prange-Quint, Undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Rassin-Risner, Undated (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Robbins-Ryan, Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Academic Career- Incoming Correspondence (S-Z), undated
  - Sachs-Schwartz, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Seacat-Shock, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Siegel-Slater, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Smalley-Souder, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Speir-Stone, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Strauss-Sweetser, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Tanaka-Thompson, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Tobias-Turner, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Valkonen-Vyas, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Walker-Warren, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Weeks-White, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Wien-Wynder, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Yarborough-Zolik, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Academic Career- Prize for Excellence in Writing, undated
  - Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Advertisements, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Overview, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Winner, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Annual reports, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Submission, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Other writing awards, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Comments by Ms. Brown, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Academic Career- Courses, undated
  - Nursing 211 Class- Midterms (Planning a Study), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Problem Solving, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Problem Solving, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Examinations, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Homework/lesson plan, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Research in nursing, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Problem Solving, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Exams copies, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Janice Ambery Critiques, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Nursing 211 Class- Janice Ambery Critiques, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Graduate Students‘ materials, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Scientific Writing Course- rough drafts, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Scientific Writing Course- correspondence, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Scientific Writing Course- book reviews, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Scientific Writing Course- letters-, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Scientific Writing Course- correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Scientific Writing Course Proposal, undated (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Scientific Writing Course Legal Pad, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Research 1 Course- library form, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Curriculum Development Course Proposal, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Graduate Students descriptions, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Academic Career- Research, undated
  - Paris School of Medicine Thesis, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Presentations and Workshops, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Vanderbilt Alumnus, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Valve Replacement Research- Grant Proposal, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Valve Replacement Research- research proposal, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cardiac Surgery reports, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Research Correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Workshops and Seminars- Tennessee Nurses Association/ANA, 1965-1969 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Presentations and Workshops, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Grant Letters, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Grant Letters, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Grant Letters, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Grant Application, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Grant Application, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Campus Map, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Presentations and Workshops, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Dissertations, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Honors/Awards, 1962-1974 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Honors/Awards- The Tennessean, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Workshops- Women and Law, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Positions/ Resumes, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Workshops/Seminars-Programs, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Meetings/Itineraries, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Employee Rights/ Equal Pay, undated (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Valve Replacement Research- Rules, undated (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Application for funds, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Participation in meetings/conferences, undated (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Medical Nursing poster, undated (Box 7, Folder 28)
- Academic Career-Research, undated
  - Teaching Family Centered Care Workshop- Discussion questions, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Teaching Family Centered Care Workshop- Bibliography, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Teaching Family Centered Care Workshop- Itineraries/Schedule, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Teaching Family Centered Care Workshop- Correspondence October-November, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Valve replacement Research- Patients List, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Veterans Research Project- Application, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Veterans Research Project- Application, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Veterans Research Project Letters, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Veterans Research Project Release Forms, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Employee Report, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Cost of Bed making Subject List, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Research Cost of Bed making, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Research Cost of Bed making Correspondence, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Research study Letters July, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Research study Letters September, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Research study Letters October, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Research study Letters November, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Research study Letters July-September, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Research Proposal, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Veterans Research Project Letters, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Grant Application, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Grant Application, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Budget for Research, 1971-1974 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Sigma Theta Tau, 1970-1976 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Research Letters, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - More Grant Applications, undated (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Energy cost of Activity by Cardiac Patients forms, undated (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Academic Career- Research, undated
  - Grant Writing/ Request for Funds May, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Grant Writing/ Request for Funds September-November, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Research Policies and Regulations, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Research Progress Reports, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Research Grant Applications, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Research Grant Applications, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Research Grant Applications, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Cost of Physical Activity to Cardiac Patients proposal, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Salary Compensations, 1963-1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Grants, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Statistics/copies from The Tennessean, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Research correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Grants, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Progress of research reports January-September, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Progress of research reports November- December, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Research Study documents, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Consent forms, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Research Proposal, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Left Ventricle Failure Research, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Grant letters March, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Biographical information of patients, undated (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Schedules for research, undated (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Grant Applications, undated (Box 9, Folder 24)
- Writings/Retirement, undated
  - Books by Amy Frances Brown, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Medical Nursing: An Outline for Teachers by Amy Frances Brown (W.B Saunders Company: Philadelphia and London 1945) -2 copies
    - Curriculum Development by Amy Frances Brown (W.B Saunders Company: Philadelphia and London 1960)
  - Books by Amy Frances Brown, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Teachers Guide to Medical Nursing Third Edition by Amy Frances Brown (W.B Saunders Company: Philadelphia and London 1960)
  - Reference book, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - The Contribution of Physical Therapy to Nursing Education by the National League of Nursing Education 1948
  - Articles by Amy Frances Brown (1950-1957), undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - “Evaluation of Performance in Motor Skills” By Amy Frances Brown. February 1, 1950
    - “Some of the Highlights Up to Now” By Amy Frances Brown. 1957
  - Articles by Amy Frances Brown, (1963-1969) (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - “Your Future as a Nurse” By Amy Frances Brown. February 17, 1963
    - “Continuity of Patient Care- In the Hospital” By Amy Frances Brown. July 7 1969 -3 copies
  - Articles by Amy Frances Brown, (1971-1979) (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - “Clinical Instruction—A means to Problem Solving” By Amy Frances Brown. February 20, 1971
    - “Growth and Development of Professional Nursing...” By Amy Frances Brown. April 17, 1972 -2 copies
    - “Cardiac Nursing Research: Past and Present” By Amy Frances Brown. April 21, 1974
    - “Teaching Nursing Students About Pain” By Amy Frances Brown
  - Presentations by Amy Frances Brown, 1964-1974 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Survey by Amy Frances Brown, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Writings, undated
  - List of Publications, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Handwritten Drafts by Amy Frances Brown (1 of 2), undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Handwritten Drafts by Amy Frances Brown (2 of 2), undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Journal- Near Christmas 1969/1970/1971; Labor Day (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Journal- near Christmas Journals, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Comments by Amy Frances Brown, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - “Improvement of Teaching Methods”
    - “Pretest for Nursing Students
  - Reviews by Amy Frances Brown- October, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Flores and Zohman Article
    - Helena Willis Render Article
- Writing by Others, 1960-1972
  - (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - “Diversity in Nurse Staffing Patterns”
    - Bibliography of references
    - Statistical Bulletin
  - (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - “Football in 1914”
    - Newspaper from 1972
  - (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - “Energy cost of bed making for Cardiac Surgery Patients”
  - Papers and Letters Record for Nursing Department, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Academic Career- VU school of Nursing newsletters, 1969-1973 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Retirement- Letters April-May, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Retirement- Guest Registry May 7th, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 22)
  - Retirement Cards, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Personal and biographical -Articles Written About her, 1974-1979 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Personal and biographical information- Will of Amy Frances Brown, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Personal and Biographical- Biographical Data, undated (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Photograph of Amy Frances Brown (Undated) (Box 10, Folder 27)